Guide to the New-York Historical Society General Correspondence 1805-2024 (bulk, 1805-1982) NYHS-RG 2
New-York Historical Society
- Series IV. General Correspondence, 1908-1982; 117.29 Linear feet in 282 document boxes and one oversize folder
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. American A-American Z (Box 189, Folder 7)
    Concerns member list of The American Association for State and Local History of which A.J. Wall (Director, N-YHS) and Dorothy C. Barck (Librarian, N-YHS), were members; N-YHS's involvement with the Museums Committee of the American Red Cross War Fund and serving as a space for the Red Cross surgical dressings; correspondence with the American Museum of Natural History requesting the N-YHS take part in Air Raid Protection for the museum and community; report for the training of archivists from Ernst Posner (Society of American Archivists); constitution of the American Association for State and Local History (formed in 1940).
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. An-Az, 1937 (Box 189, Folder 8)
    Concerns the publication, The Odyssey of the Mary Celeste, presented to the Society by the Atlantic Mutual Insurance Company on the company's 100th Anniversary; extensive correspondence between Joseph Atz (Lawyer) and N-YHS discusses the estate of Kate C. Jones (caricatures, maps, prints, etc. of the period 1836-50 and William George Stewart letters).
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Associated Hospital Service of New York, 1937 (Box 189, Folder 9)
    Concerns general enrollment in the service between 1939 and 1942; updated health insurance contract for N-YHS employees; fees for enrollment, and related matters.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Ba, 1937 (Box 189, Folder 10)
    Concerns the East Hampton Thompson estate opening reception and letter to Mayor Judson L. Banister to say a few words of welcome; correspondence from genealogist Rosalie Fellows Bailey.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Banks, James Lenox (Box 189, Folder 11)
    Concerns Fourth Vice-President James Lenox Banks' role on the N-YHS's Safety Committee and the preparations N-YHS made to safeguard the collections in case of air raids during the war, including the use of a secure location in the Pocono Mountains; donations made by Banks to Society, and other matters.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Be (Box 189, Folder 12)
    Concerns the potential acquisition of the coach Lincoln was driven in while visiting Trenton, New Jersey owned by John Dunn Buckelew; Frequent correspondent: William E. Benjamin.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Beekman, Fenwick Dr. (Box 190, Folder 1)
    Dr. Fenwick Beekman (second Vice-President, N-YHS) served on the Committee of Safety. Concerns Beekman Family Association furniture, tapestries, and cradle as used in the "old Beekman House on 49th street," gifted to the N-YHS in 1910.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Benson, Arthur D. (Box 190, Folder 2)
    Arthur D. Benson was a descendant of Lt. Col. Robert Benson (1739-1832), who served as Aide-de-Camp to Governor George Clinton in the American Revolution, as well as the descendant of Judge Egbert Benson (1746-1833), N-YHS's first President. Several letters discuss the burial place of Judge Egbert Benson in Prospect Cemetery; several items presented to the N-YHS; Washington Inaugural scene at 1939 World's Fair.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Benson, Judge Egbert (Box 190, Folder 3)
    Concerns the bronze tablet designed for the gravesite of Judge Egbert Benson (1746-1833), N-YHS's first President, in Prospect Cemetery, Jamaica, NY.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Benson, Hevlyn D. (Box 190, Folder 4)
    Concerns the rededication of St. Paul's Church (Eastchester, Mount Vernon) following its restoration, and includes copies of article discussing the ceremony.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Bi-Bl (Box 190, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Blizzard Men of 1888 (Box 190, Folder 6)
    Concerns a prize essay on the Blizzard of 1888 and meeting announcements for the Association.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Bo-Bry (Box 190, Folder 7)
    Concerns the acquisition of 158 World War I posters from Laurence P. Roberts (Director, The Brooklyn Museum); announcement of death of Reginald Pelham Bolton; precautions taken by the Brooklyn Museum to safeguard collections during the war; letter from Boyce, Hughes, & Farrell (Certified Public Accountants) in regard to N-YHS balance sheet dated December 31, 1939.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Bu-By (Box 190, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Caa-Car (Box 190, Folder 9)
    Concerns bequest from Rev. Melancthon Lloyd Woolsey to N-YHS.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Carnegie Corporation of New York (Box 190, Folder 10)
    Concerns the $15,000 grant to the N-YHS for the Carnegie Corporation's program in American painting, including annual reports submitted to the Corporation on the progress made under the grant.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Carney, Dr. Sydney, Jr. (Box 190, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Ch-Clo (Box 190, Folder 12)
    Concerns the Committee on Cultural Resources appointed by the N-YHS to prepare materials for transport in case of bombing during the war; letter discusses skylights being covered and sand being placed on top floors.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Coa-Col (Box 190, Folder 13)
    Concerns photographs for portraits for William Sawitzky's lectures for the "Early American Painting" course.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Color Slides Cooperative (Box 190, Folder 14)
    Color Slides Cooperative was created in 1939 as a method by which "recently developed slides could be made available to education institutions throughout the country." Concerns the cooperation of the N-YHS for the series of color slides issues by Color Slides Cooperative, Survey of American Painting, and The Collections of the National Gallery of Art; includes bulletins for the Cooperative Slide Project.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Columbia University (Box 190, Folder 15)
    Consists mainly of correspondence between A.J.Wall (Director, N-YHS) and the Columbia University Press on publications and other matters.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Columbia University (A.J.Wall's class) (Box 190, Folder 16)
    Concerns the course A.J.Wall (Director, N-YHS) gave at Columbia University in 1942, "History 280: Resources and Methods of the American Historical Society Library and Museum;" includes lecture outlines.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Committee on Conservation of Cultural Resources (Box 190, Folder 17)
    The Committee on Conservation of Cultural Resources was established in 1941 to prepare and plan for the protection of materials of cultural, scientific, and historic importance in Federal agencies; Includes paper, "Archives and the War," presented by Collas G. Harris (Chairman of the Committee) at the 64th Annual Conference; discussion of the danger posed by skylights durng war time and the protection of collections.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Conference of Historical Societies (Box 190, Folder 18)
    Documentation includes a preliminary draft of the Report of the Policy Committee; N-YHS served as host for meetings.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Con-Cor (Box 190, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Correspondence Logs, 1940-1941 (Box 190, Folder 20)
    Consists of two logbooks that captured dates and names of incoming correspondence, as well as when replies were sent out.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Cos-Coz (Box 190, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Cr (Box 190, Folder 22)
    Concerns gifts made by Henry Chauncey Cryder to the N-YHS.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Cu-Cy (Box 191, Folder 1)
    Concerns the Port of New York Room at the N-YHS that contained the pictures of all types of boats that entered NY harbor, and the presentation of a picture of the Queen Mary and oil painting of the steamship Olympic from Cunard White Star Line.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Da (Box 191, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. De (Box 191, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. DeGroot, Adelaide Milton (Box 191, Folder 4)
    Concerns the various donations made to the Society by Adelaide Milton de Groot, descendant of Honorable Charles Hawley, Lieutenant Governor of Connecticut.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Delafield, John Ross (Box 191, Folder 5)
    Concerns the items presented to the N-YHS from General John Ross Delafield.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Delafield, Lewis L. (Box 191, Folder 6)
    Concerns the revision of N-YHS's by-laws.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Dioramas (Rudolph Russell) (Box 191, Folder 7)
    Rudolph Russell was a diorama maker. Correspondence discusses Russell's specifications for diorama of Battery Park for the N-YHS.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Di (Box 191, Folder 8)
    Concerns the donations of several items to the Landauer Collection, including match box covers and meal bags; letter from Walt Disney Productions in regard to sending a bookplate of Mr. Disney to the N-YHS.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Do (Box 191, Folder 9)
    Consists of mention of the Folk Art Gallery formerly owned by Elie Nadelman.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Dowling, Robert E. (Box 191, Folder 10)
    Robert E. Dowling served on the Executive Committee and as Second Vice President of N-YHS. Includes biography; committee appointed by President Zabriskie to "consider the verbal offer of Mr. Robert W. Dowling to acquire and present to the Society the Old Merchant's House at 29 East Fourth Street...as a memorial to his father the late Robert E. Dowling," declined by the N-YHS; investments in the Certified Mortgage issues held by the Society.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Dr (Box 191, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Du-Dy (Box 191, Folder 12)
    Frequent correspondent: Henry F. DuPont.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Ea-Ek (Box 191, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. El-Ez (Box 191, Folder 14)
    Separated Materials Note
    Concerns the gift of various Ellis family items to the Society by Mrs. Augustus Van Horne Ellis.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Evans, Lena Cadwalader (Box 191, Folder 15)
    Consists primarily of the many gifts presented to the N-YHS by Lena Cadwalader Evans.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Early American Industries Association, 1938-1941 (Box 191, Folder 16)
    Concerns administrative issues including member lists of the Association, founded by William B. Sprague. A.J. Wall (Director, N-YHS) served as President.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Early American Industries Association (2 folders) (Box 192, Folder 1-2)
    Concerns administrative issues; minutes; membership lists in the Association; the Chronicle (publication) of the Association.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. East Hampton (MISC.) (Box 192, Folder 3)
    Consists of exchanges between A.J.Wall (Director, N-YHS) and the East Hampton Historical Society in regard to the Dominy Collection; includes letters in regard to East Hampton Thompson Memorial Homestead, a satellite museum operated during the summer by the N-YHS.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Fa-Fl (Box 192, Folder 4)
    Correspondence between Stanley M. Isaacs (President, Borough of Manhattan), Joseph Downs (Curator, Metropolitan Museum of Art), and others discuss the proposal to build a Battery Park Memorial Museum to preserve many of the interiors of old homes that were being demolished as a result of the Battery Tunnel construction.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Fahnestock, Harris (Box 192, Folder 5)
    Harris Fahnestock was a donor to the Society who presented his horse-drawn carriage collection and publications about carriages to the N-YHS. The collection included various types of carriages including a Brougham, Panel Boot Victoria, Demi-mail phaeton, and Stanhope gig.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Florida Historical Society (Box 192, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Fo (Box 192, Folder 7)
    Concerns first drafts of the Hamilton-Burr duel correspondence in letters to St. George L. Sioussat of the Library of Congress allowing permission to photostat the collection consisting of close to 300 documents written between 1779 and 1837; Frequent correspondent: The Folk Arts Center (Elizabeth Burchenel).
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Foreign (Box 192, Folder 8)
    Concerns the display cases at the N-YHS as made by Remington Rand, Inc.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Fr-Fu, 1938-1942, 1971 (Box 192, Folder 9)
    Includes clipping from The Morning Telegraph in regard to the exhibitions displaying Landauer's collection of trade cards and advertising materials, as well as theatrical materials; note from registrar documenting that doll belonging to Mrs. Rudolph Guiterman presented to the N-YHS in 1942 was returned to Mrs. M.R. Friedman in 1971 (1942.259); The Franklin Society thanking N-YHS for its cooperation with the Dutch window exhibit.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Ga (Box 192, Folder 10)
    Concerns acquisitions to the Landauer collection;Thompson memorial room built in connection to the estate at East Hampton, Long Island.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Gallatin, R.Horace (Box 192, Folder 11)
    Concerns notices of meetings for committees that Gallatin was involved with, and his participation in the plans for the construction of the new building.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Ge (Box 192, Folder 12)
    Frequent correspondent: Raoul Gerard.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Gillingham, Harrold E. (Box 192, Folder 13)
    Harrold E. Gillingham was President of the Genealogical Society of Pennsylvania. Primarily concerns A.J.Wall speaking at the Genealogical Society and Gillingham's donations to the N-YHS. Includes discussion of the precautions N-YHS took during the war, such as moving materials out of the building and covering skylights, while anti-air craft guns were in Central Park.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Gh-Gn (Box 192, Folder 14)
    Concerns acquisitions to the Landauer Collection.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Go (Box 192, Folder 15)
    Concerns acquisitions to the Landauer Collection; report presented to the N-YHS of the engineering details of the construction of the Golden Gate Bridge; orders of bronze plaques from the Gorham Company, including the tablet for the base of the obelisk," Cleopatra's Needle" in Central Park.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Gr-Gy (Box 193, Folder 1)
    Concerns the reception commemorating the 20th anniversary of the Greenwich Village Historical Society (GVHS); symposium of prominent persons in history, art, literature, and civics arranged by the GVHS to express value of preserving Fort Clinton; brochure and application receipts for the John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, established by former U.S. Senator and Mrs. Simon Guggenheim as a memorial to a son who died April 26, 1922, which offered fellowships for research "in any field of knowledge and for creative work in any of the fine arts"; re-opening of museum.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Green, Norvin H. (Box 193, Folder 2)
    Norvin H. Green was a member of the Board of Trustees and he donated books to the Society on various subjects including New York ferries, in addition to photographs, negatives, prints and other matter.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Griffith, Dr. Frederick (Box 193, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Groce, George C. Jr. (Box 193, Folder 4)
    Concerns William Sawitzky's series of lectures for the "Early American Painting" course.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Grolier Club (Box 193, Folder 5)
    Concerns loans to the Grolier Club for exhibitional purposes, including an item from the Eugene H. Pool Collection of Captain James Lawrence for an exhibition of prints of naval engagements at the Grolier Club.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Prosper Guerry Studios (Box 193, Folder 6)
    Concerns invoices for portrait restoration work done by Prosper Guerry Studios.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Haa-Hal (Box 193, Folder 7)
    Concerns President Taft portrait painted by Artur L. Halmi in the White House in 1912, and purchased by the N-YHS; includes letters from President Taft's son, Robert A. Taft; Embargo (1807-1809) as it affected the Champlain Valley discussed in the Gallatin papers; clippings in regard to feedback to The Exquisite Siren, written by E. Irvine Haines, to the story about Peggy Shippen and Benedict Arnold. Frequent correspondent: Herbert D. Halsey.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Hale, Nathan (Box 193, Folder 8)
    Concerns Dr. John Lydekker's (Society for the Propagation of the Gospel in Foreign Parts) letter on the subject of Nathan Hale; George Seymour's Documentary Life of Nathan Hale; correspondence relating to the mystery surrounding the capture and execution of Hale.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Hamersley, L. Gordon (Box 193, Folder 9)
    Hamersley was a member of the Board of Trustees.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Hart, Laurance H. (Box 193, Folder 10)
    Laurance H. Hart was an impersonator of George Washington who appeared in many radio programs, conventions, and institutions, including the N-YHS.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Ham-Har (Box 193, Folder 11)
    Majority correspondence concerns gifts to N-YHS by various individuals.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Has-Haz (Box 193, Folder 12)
    Concerns proposed publication of a series of monographs on "Early American Portraiture" by William Sawitzky; appointment of A.J.Wall (Director, N-YHS) to Associate in History at Columbia University; donation of the McDougall and Hawkes letters from Mrs. Forbes Hawkes (Alice S. Hawkes).
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. He (Box 193, Folder 13)
    Concerns the presentation to the Society of photographic prints and plates of the Cathedral of St. John the Divine photographed between 1894-1938 from Mrs. Antoinette B. Hervey.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Heartman, Charles F. (Box 193, Folder 14)
    Correspondence mentions of A.J.Wall Jr. entering the service, and the shortage of library staff due to war enlistment.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Heat and Light (Box 193, Folder 15)
    Concerns the average heating and electricity consumption and related costs of the N-YHS; includes report on power and heat problem undertaken by William H. Dechant and Sons, Consulting Engineers.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Hi (Box 193, Folder 16)
    Frequent correspondent: John Hix.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Hoa-Hom (Box 193, Folder 17)
    Concerns patrolman reports of the museum by the Holmes Patrol.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Hone, Augustus C. (Box 194, Folder 1)
    Augustus C. Hone was the fourth Vice-President of the N-YHS. Some correspondence was exchanged between Hone's widow, Alice Castleman Hone, and A.J. Wall (Director, N-YHS).
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Hon-Hoz (Box 194, Folder 2)
    Concerns the removal of and returning of valuable materials on loan from exhibition and closing the top floor of the gallery for the duration of the war in case of air raids; Frequent correspondent: Marian Sadtler Hornor.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Hoffman, Eugene A. (Box 194, Folder 3)
    Eugene A. Hoffman was a member of the Board of Trustees.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Hoffman, Samuel V. (Box 194, Folder 4)
    Concerns the death of Samuel V. Hoffman (President, N-YHS) in 1942. Includes a Memorial presented at a Board meeting of Mr. Hoffman's many contributions and benefactions to the N-YHS.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Holloway, H. Maxson (Box 194, Folder 5)
    H. Maxson Holloway was employed as Curator at the N-YHS. Concerns Holloway's enlistment in the army.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Hu (2 folders) (Box 194, Folder 6-7)
    Concerns efforts by the Hudson River Conservation Society to stop quarrying along the Hudson River and preserve High Tor (mountain overlooking Haverstraw Bay) and other locations; floating "classroom" with nearly 500 Society members attending a six hour course in New York history aboard the Hudson River Day Liner Chauncey M. Depew; Nathan Hale clippings from the Brooklyn Eagle.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Huntington, Archer M. (Box 194, Folder 8)
    Archer M. Huntington was elected as Foreign Corresponding Secretary of the N-YHS.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Henry E. Huntington Library (Box 194, Folder 9)
    Concerns the type of masthead used by the Huntington Library for publicity releases.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Hy (Box 194, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Ib-Il (Box 194, Folder 11)
    Concerns the protection of State records during the war and exchanges between A.J.Wall and Margaret C. Norton (Archivist, Illinois State Library) on the collection of data on this subject from various states, as well as the steps N-YHS was taking to ensure the protection of its collections.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Im-In (Box 194, Folder 12)
    Concerns lecture by Pierre Huss of International News Service; installation of revolving door approved by Garrett H. Winter (Superintendent, N-YHS).
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Io-Ir (Box 194, Folder 13)
    Concerns the Iowa War Records Commission that consisted of trained historians, librarians, business executives, public archival administrators and others for the collection and preservation of Iowa's contributions and participation in World War II.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Irwin, John V. (Box 195, Folder 1)
    Concerns his role as Board of Trustees member in approving lecture program schedule, etc; includes several of his donations to the Society.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Ja (Box 195, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Jamaica, Institute of (British West Indies) (Box 195, Folder 3)
    Concerns the Frank Cundall Memorial Fund. Frank Cundall was Secretary and Librarian of the Institute of Jamaica (1891-1937).
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Jamaica, B.W.I. Naval Records at Spanishtown (Box 195, Folder 4)
    Concerns the copying of the American naval (Vice-Admiralty) records unearthed in the Island Record office and stored in the old Armoury, Spanish Town, Jamaica.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Je-Ji (Box 195, Folder 5)
    Exchanges between A.J.Wall (Director, N-YHS) and Fiske Kimball (Director, Philadelphia Museum of Art) discuss the request to the N-YHS to make a mold of its Houdon Jefferson bust for the memorial to Thomas Jefferson in Washington, D.C.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Is-Iz (Box 195, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Jo-Jz (2 folders) (Box 195, Folder 7-8)
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Johnson, C.K. (Box 195, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Jones, Arthur A. (Box 195, Folder 10)
    Arthur A. Jones was a member of the Board of Trustees and President of the Cedango Corporation for Investment Securities.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Jones, Matt B. (Box 195, Folder 11)
    Matt B. Jones served as Librarian of the Club of Odd Volumes.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Ka (Box 195, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Ke (Box 195, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Kelleher, William F. (Box 195, Folder 14)
    William F. Kelleher specialized in appraisals of rare Americana, first editions, prints, and paintings.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Ki (2 folders) (Box 195, Folder 15-16)
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Kimball, Leroy E. (Box 196, Folder 1)
    Concerns the potential publication of a second volume of the history of the N-YHS, covering the years between 1904 and 1944 and other matters.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Kl (Box 196, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Kn (Box 196, Folder 3)
    Concerns the Last Will and Testament of Elizabeth B. Knight and her bequest to the Society of several Bleecker family items.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Knoedler & Company., Inc. (Box 196, Folder 4)
    M. Knoedler & Co was an art dealership in New York City founded in 1846. Concerns various items presented to the Society by the firm or loaned for N-YHS exhibitions.
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Ko (Box 196, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence 1938-1942. Kr (Box 196, Folder 6)